



Ciara Keenan, PhD, MSc, BSc (Hons)

Research Fellow | Campbell UK & Ireland

Post-doctoral researcher with strong quantitative background and an established international reputation in evidence synthesis methodology. Throughout my higher education and post-doctoral posts, I have been most responsive to research investigating how inequalities shape society and how these poor outcomes can be transgenerational.

Fields of concentration: systematic review, meta-analysis, race, ethnicity, diversity, homelessness, disability, vulnerable and marginalised groups, post conflict society.

Education

MSc Biostatistics (NUIG, current)

Dissertation: Examining solutions to the missingness issue in meta-analysis.

Supervisor: Professor John Newell

PhD Sociology/Psychology (QUB, 2018)

Dissertation: Universal Preschool- and School-based Education Programmes for Reducing Ethnic Prejudice and Promoting Respect for Diversity among Children Aged 3-11: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis.

Supervisors: Professor Paul Connolly, Dr Clifford Stevenson, and Dr Laura Taylor

MSc Autism Spectrum Disorders (QUB, 2014)

Dissertation: Video-based interventions for promoting positive social behaviour in children with autism spectrum disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis.

Supervisor: Professor Allen Thurston

BSc (Hons) Social Psychology (UUC, 2009)

Employment

Research Fellow, Campbell UK & Ireland. 2017 – present

Associate Director, Cochrane Ireland. 2020

Editorial Assistant, Cochrane. 2017

Systematic Reviewer, Klejnen Systematic Reviews Ltd., 2017



Selected Research Grants (2020-21)

- COHERE Phase 2: Suite of living systematic reviews on determinants of COVID Health Related Behaviour (April 2021- October 2022) Funder: UKRI COVID Rolling Call (£380,000) Role: Co-Investigator
- A rapid EGM on education research during COVID-19 (March June 2021). Funder:
 Department of Education, Northern Ireland (£15,000) Role: Co-Investigator
- A rapid systematic review on Kidney research during COVID-19 (June August 2020).
 Funder: Insilica LLC. (\$2,000) Role: Principal Investigator
- Three systematic reviews on the prevention of homelessness (Jan-Sept 2019). Funder:
- Crisis UK (£157,680). Role: Co-Investigator

Other Funding

- 2016 BERA student bursary to attend BERA conference
- 2015 Emily Sarah Montgomery travel scholarship to travel to Nashville
- 2014 DEL studentship to complete PhD research
- 2014 Smith Richardson Foundation research grant to employ four coders on PhD project

Professional Affiliations, activities and honours

- Organising committee of the <u>Evidence Synthesis Hackathon</u>, 2021
- Organising committee of Virtually Cochrane, 2021
- Steering group for Priority III, Evidence Synthesis Ireland 2020 present.
- Campbell's working group for Meta-Reviews 2020- present.
- Review Panel for shortlisted grants, CEDIL commissioned projects 2019.
- Grant peer reviewer, CEDIL commissioned projects 2019.
- Methods Editor, Campbell Collaboration 2018 present.
- Information retrieval specialist, Campbell Collaboration 2017 present.
- Founder and Editor, Meta-Evidence blog 2018 present.
- Co-convenor, Campbell's information retrieval group 2018- present.



Selected invited talks and teaching (2020- 21)

GESI – Campbell Collaboration webinar series. Searching in Campbell reviews: Improving and creating the evidence base (Online - webinar) 13 July 2021. Role: Facilitator.

International Collaboration for the Automation of Systematic Reviews. (Online conference) 12th April 2021. Role: Speaker.

Housing studies association. (Online meeting) 13th November 2020. Role: Speaker.

OECD Centre for Education Research and Innovation panel. COVID-19: implications for education experts and evidence. (Online meeting) 28 May 2020. Role: Speaker.

GESI – Campbell Collaboration webinar series. Plain Language Summaries: Improving the reach of your Systematic Review (Online - webinar) 28 May 2020. Role: Facilitator.

Teaching / supervision experience

Current Teaching and/or Supporting Learning Roles at Queen's	Dates
Co-facilitator of 2-day online workshop on Evidence and Gap Maps. Ran for Campbell UK	4 th -5 th May
& Ireland within Centre for Evidence and Social Innovation (CESI) (8 hours)	2021
Provision of ongoing mentorship to an Evidence Synthesis Ireland fellow based in Queen's.	Mar 2021
This fellowship was a competitive process which provides the fellow the opportunity to	
learn more about evidence synthesis from an experienced methodologist, such as myself	
(approx. 2 hours per week).	
I am currently mentoring various academic staff from QUB, helping them undertake	Nov 2017 -
evidence syntheses within the Cochrane/Campbell framework (approx.1 hour per week).	ongoing
An advisory role for a PhD student at the School of Education and Centre for Public Health	Dec 2020 -
at Queen's University Belfast (approx.1 hour per week).	ongoing
Primary supervisor for a master's student (student one) at the School of Education at	Mar – Nov
Queen's University Belfast (approx.1 hour per week).	2020
Primary supervisor for a master's student (student 2) at the School of Education at Queen's	Mar – May
University Belfast (approx.1 hour per week).	2020
Facilitator of full day in-person workshop on Advanced search methods for systematic	Nov 2018
reviews and meta-analysis in school of Medicine, Dentistry and Biomedical Sciences (7	
hours)	



	June 202
Co-facilitator of three day in-person workshop on Introduction to Systematic Reviews &	May 2018
Evidence and Gap Maps for Campbell UK and Ireland within Centre for Evidence and	
Social Innovation (CESI) (12 hours)	
Facilitator of full day in-person workshop on Advanced search methods for systematic	Nov 2017
reviews and meta-analysis in school of Medicine, Dentistry and Biomedical Sciences (7	
hours)	
Teaching and/or Supporting Learning Roles outside Queen's	Dates
Primary supervisor of a Master's student at the School of Nursing & Midwifery, NUI	Nov 2020 -
Galway (approx.1 hour per week).	ongoing
Co-facilitator of 3 full day in-person workshop (21 hours) on Systematic reviews. Ran for	Feb 2019
Campbell Collaboration in Lanzhou University, China (12 hours)	
Plain Language Summaries: Improving the reach of your Systematic Review. GESI –	May 2020
Campbell Collaboration webinar series (1 hour webinar)	
Effective searching. Cochrane Ireland (20-minute online video)	Nov 2020
Plain Language Summaries. Cochrane Colloquium (1.5 hour workshop).	Sep 2018

Recent Publications

- **Keenan, C.,** Noone, C., McConnell, K., Cheng S.H. (2021). A rapid response to the COVID-19 outbreak: the meta-evidence project. *Journal of EAHIL*, 17 (2)
- **Keenan, C.,** Miller, S., Hanratty, J., Pigott, T. D., Hamilton, J., Coughlan, C., . . . Cowman, J. (2021). Accommodation-based interventions for individuals experiencing, or at risk of experiencing, homelessness. *Campbell Systematic Reviews*, 17(2), e1165. doi:https://doi.org/10.1002/c12.1165
- **Keenan, C.,** Thurston, A., Storey, C., & Urbanska, K. PROTOCOL: Video-based interventions for promoting positive social behaviour in children with autism spectrum disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. *Campbell Systematic Reviews*. 2021; 17:e1171. https://doi.org/10.1002/cl2.1171
- Gillies, K., Kearney, A., **Keenan, C.,** Treweek, S., Hudson, J., Brueton, V. C., . . . et al. (2021). Strategies to improve retention in randomised trials. *Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews*(3). doi:10.1002/14651858.MR000032.pub3
- Haddaway, N. R., Akl, E. A., Page, M. J., Welch, V. A., **Keenan, C.,** & Lotfi, T. (2020). Open synthesis and the coronavirus pandemic in 2020. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology, 126, 184-191.





- Burke, N. N., Galvin, S., Devane, D., & **Keenan, C.** (2020). COVID-19 Emergency Evidence Response Service: report from Ireland. *Collaborating in response to COVID-19: editorial and methods initiatives across Cochrane. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews, 12.*
- Mahalingasivam, V., Craik, A., Tomlinson, L. A., Ge, L., Hou, L., Wang, Q., . . . **Keenan, C.** (2020). COVID-19 and kidney transplantation: A systematic review. Kidney international reports.
- Hennessy, E. A., Johnson, B. T., & **Keenan**, C. (2019). Best practice guidelines and essential methodological steps to conduct rigorous and systematic meta-reviews. *Applied Psychology: Health and Well-Being*, 11(3), 353-381.
- Connolly, P., **Keenan, C.,** & Urbanska, K. (2018). The trials of evidence-based practice in education: a systematic review of randomised controlled trials in education research 1980–2016. *EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH*, 60(3), 276-291.
- Riemsma R, Corro Ramos I, Thielen F, Fayter D, Armstrong N, Wei C-Y, **Keenan C,** Huertas Carrera V, Büyükkaramikli N, Misso K, Worthy G, Kleijnen J. (2017). Obinutuzumab for untreated advanced follicular lymphoma: A Single Technology Assessment for NICE. York: Kleijnen Systematic Reviews Ltd.
- Riemsma R, Corro Ramos, I, Büyükkaramikli N, Fayter D, Armstrong N, **Keenan C**, Swift S, Huertas Carrera V, Misso K, Worthy G, Al M, Kleijnen J. (2017). Grazoprevir–elbasvir for treating chronic hepatitis C: A Single Technology Assessment for NICE. York: Kleijnen Systematic Reviews Ltd.

Protocols, Preprints and papers in press

- In press: **Keenan, C.,** Connolly, P., Urbanska, K., & Taylor, L. (2021). Universal preschool-and school-based education programmes for reducing ethnic prejudice and promoting respect for diversity among children aged 3-11: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Campbell Systematic Reviews
- Published protocol: **Keenan, C.,** Miller, S., Hanratty, J., Pigott, T. D., Mackie, P., Cowman, J., ... & Fitzpatrick, S. (2020). PROTOCOL: Accommodation-based interventions for individuals experiencing, or at risk of experiencing, homelessness. Campbell Systematic Reviews, 16(3), e1103.
- Published protocol: Bergero, G., **Keenan, C.,** & Liew, A. (2021). PROTOCOL: The efficacy and safety profile of leptin replacement therapy for non-HAART associated lipodystrophic





- syndromes: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Inplasy protocol 202110047. doi:10.37766/inplasy2021.1.0047
- Published protocol: Maynard, B. R., Duvendack, M., Hennessy, E. A., **Keenan, C.,** Lunny, C., & Welch, V. A. (2021). Protocol: Methodological Expectations of Campbell Collaboration Intervention Meta-Reviews: Conduct and Reporting Standards. Retrieved from osf.io/knvg4
- Published protocol: Carvalho, C., & **Keenan, C.** (2021). PROTOCOL: Nurses' knowledge about Palliative Care in long term care facilities for older people: A scoping review. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14040035.v3
- Published protocol: **Keenan, C.,** Pigott, T.D., Newell, J. (2020). PROTOCOL: Examining solutions to the missingness issue in meta-analysis: A Systematic Review. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.13270298.v1
- Published protocol: Cáceres-Escobar, H., Broad, S., Challender, D. W. S., Kinnaird, M. F., **Keenan, C.,** Lichtenstein, G., Rodriguez, J. P., Roe, D., Rouan, A. D., Van Dijk, P. P., Zambrana-Torrelio, C., & Kock, R. (2020). PROTOCOL: an Evidence and Gap Map (EGM) about the Roles and Risks of Wildlife Trade in the Emergence of Human Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.13392275.v2
- Published protocol: Hull, K.L., Selvaskandan, H., Cheung, C.K., Keenan, C., Simmons, B., Lightstone, L., Griffith, M., Ge, L., Zhu, H., Lim M. PROTOCOL: Evaluating the impact of immunosuppressive agents used for the treatment of auto-immune kidney disease on COVID-19 severity: A systematic review. PROSPERO 2020 CRD42020226260 Available from: https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42020226260
- Published protocol: Miller, S., **Keenan, C.,** Hanratty, J., Hamilton, J., Coughlan, C., Mackie, P., ... & Maddock, A. (2020) PROTOCOL: Improving access to health and social services for individuals experiencing, or at risk of experiencing, homelessness. Campbell Systematic Reviews, 16(3), e1109.
- Published protocol: Hanratty, J., Miller, S., **Keenan, C.,** Cowman, J., Hamilton, J., & Mackie, P. (2020). PROTOCOL: Discharge programmes for individuals experiencing, or at risk of experiencing, homelessness: A systematic review. Campbell Systematic Reviews, 16(3), e1109.



June 2021

- Protocol in press: Vasconcello-Castillo L, Torres-Castro R, **Keenan C,** Collins K, Solís-Navarro L, Cano-Cappellacci M, Vilaró J. Exercise after bariatric surgery for obese adults. *Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews*. Art. No.: CD014894.
- Protocol in press: Young S, Bethel A, **Keenan C**, Ghezzi-Kopel K, Moreton E, Pickup D, Premji ZA, Rogers M, Arleth Viinholt BC. Searching and reporting in Campbell Collaboration systematic reviews: An assessment of current methods. *Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews*. Art. No.: CA000196.
- Protocol in press: Maynard B, Maynard JA, **Keenan C.** High School Esports: Describing the Current State of the Literature and Exploring Effects on Student Outcomes. *Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews*. Art. No.: CA000197.
- Protocol in press: Haddaway N, **Keenan C**, Young S, Kohl C. Bibliographic database searching methods across CEE and Campbell Collaboration systematic reviews and maps: a systematic review. *Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews*. Art. No.: CA000232.
- Protocol in press: Liew, A., **Keenan C.** (2021) The clinical outcomes of optimal versus suboptimal time in blood glucose range among critically ill patients receiving intravenous insulin therapy: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Inplasy
- Published protocol: **Keenan, C.,** Connolly, P., & Stevenson, C. (2016). PROTOCOL: universal preschool-and school-based education programmes for reducing ethnic prejudice and promoting respect for diversity among children aged 3-11: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Campbell Systematic Reviews, 12(1), 1-45.

Masters Students (2020-21)

- Cristiana Carvalho, Master's student at the School of Nursing & Midwifery, NUI Galway. **Project:** Nurses' knowledge about Palliative Care in long term care facilities for older people: A scoping review.
- Rachel Charles, Master's student at the School of Education at Queen's University Belfast. **Project:** food selectivity in children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)
- Roberta Mallia, Master's student at the School of Education at Queen's University Belfast. **Project:** The application of Applied Behaviour Analysis principles to the treatment of Restricted and Repetitive Behaviours in individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder





Advisory Role (2020- 21)

Aideen Johnson, PhD student at the School of Education and Centre for Public Health at Queen's University Belfast. Project: An EGM on physical activity in schools

Dr Karen McConnell, ESI fellow at Campbell UK & Ireland in Queen's University Belfast.

Project: Video-based interventions in children with Autism Spectrum Disorders